[SPEAKER_00]: I thought just to ask some things which I find in the suttas relating to stages of ārya-pūgala and also inside elements like eight emancipations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll read later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm referring to the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to tell you Nikāya-4.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suttas which are... Suttas 87 to 90.
[SPEAKER_00]: In those suttas, Buddha is talking about four kinds of persons found existing in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he categorized those four people, those four persons.
[SPEAKER_00]: One is the ascetic and shaykhan.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shaykhan is the white lotus ascetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, it's just referring to sotāpanna, sakadāgāmī, anagāmī, and arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And each sutta describes these ārya-pūgalās slightly differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I put them kind of together.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I will just read some qualities of sotāpanna, which are usually quite
[SPEAKER_00]: We are familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, with a utter destruction of three fetters, a big-wis stream-enterer, who dwells aspiring for the unsurpassed security from bondage, he's one of right view, and other... this means like he's the one of the right faithful noble path, and who has not attained his mind's ideal.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I just take... stay here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe I'm interested, actually, what is the mind's ideal in this sutra?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, first of all, the point is to be an arhat, to be completely free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not quite there yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this whole quote is not referred to later on for sakadāgāmī, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to pass security from bondage?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, here, I don't have a particular question for the panel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the second thing is, is sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, here, with the utter destruction of three fetters, and with diminishing of great hatred and delusion, a vehicle is one, one's returner,
[SPEAKER_00]: who, after coming back to this world only one more time, will make an end of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, with the destruction of the taints, Adhikūra has to realize for himself direct knowledge, in this very life, the taintless liberation of mind, liberation by wisdom, and having entered upon it, he dwells in it, yet he does not dwell having contacted with the body the eight emancipations.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just the right view, right intention, and other right qualities, the way for a faithful noble path, but also right knowledge and the right liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: This is sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: He dwells contemplating arising and vanishing for the five aggregates subject to assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, this is really kind of different, described, and sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, the most interesting one was that he has also right knowledge and right liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... those two are the ones that Arahant develops, which is why he become... perfect, which is why he becomes fully enlightened Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was the right knowledge and right liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: There were other suttas when that's mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: But those two are basically... he has them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think he has a... he has a notion of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, think of sakadāgāmī as a sotāpanna who has applied himself more than just a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, he starts gaining more of that knowledge, more of that liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it becomes almost like a discernible phenomenon, discernible factor.
[SPEAKER_01]: But only an arahant has fully developed those, which is why he's an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is... what do we mean by knowledge and right liberation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it means just the continuation of the Noble Life Path.
[SPEAKER_01]: If those are developed, then he doesn't have to keep doing it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: He becomes it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for Sotāpanna, well, for all the areas, the Noble Eightfold Path, they need to keep applying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep sort of sticking to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep finding energy for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep resisting distraction against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that's brought to fulfillment, then it's just the right knowledge and the right liberation is the result of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And will be there, I feel like, for sakadāgāmī, or for this kind of person, clear distinction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, I'm no longer sotāpanna, I'm sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, actually, sakadāgāmī quite skips.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I don't think there will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it depends on the faculties of sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might be... Well, if his faculties are sharper, he might see that the... a more perceivable difference between the... when he was a sotāpanna, and then after he is sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: weakened the the other factor of sensuality and ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not... it's not... it's just a gradual weakening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, so you can look back and say, yeah, I'm stronger than when I had the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, how much stronger?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm not free from sensuality, which means then I might be, at most, sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to be free from sensuality, then, you know, okay, so I'm so...
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, if the Buddha never laid out these four, kind of,
[SPEAKER_01]: Cornerstones, these four kind of guidelines, milestones, not cornerstones, milestones.
[SPEAKER_01]: You, they wouldn't have known.
[SPEAKER_01]: All they would have known is, yeah, I've understood the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, my, my lust and aversion have been kind of lessened because of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, oh yeah, I don't have any more lust nor aversion because of this dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, oh, my mind is completely bright and pure, free from suffering and supreme security of bondage.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they wouldn't have called it in those terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha laid it out only after, like, a constant, kind of, being harassed by questions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, where is such and such monk reborn?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is this?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people wanted to know how far they were in their practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they would say, well, it's it's a real hassle.
[SPEAKER_01]: If every time somebody dies, you come and talk to me and ask me about him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... And he laid out these criterias.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's just like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: That's kind of a general sort of criteria of the state.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you know, because there's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if you included it, but there's another sutta about Sotāpanna, where basically says... well, the common sort of description is that seven lifetimes at most.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is one sutta that says Sotāpanna dies, and basically, while he's still in that experience of death, he becomes an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, I think the other one is, while he's in between, kind of, because he becomes an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, while he's getting ready to be reborn, or something like that, he becomes an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he becomes an arahant upon landing, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: upon being reborn.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, yeah, it's at most...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, you give a general description.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will include everybody who would be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean the sotāpanna has to go through seven.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just depends how much he has applied himself
[SPEAKER_01]: How much of these upatās he has sort of abolished or weakened, and then... and how clear his knowledge is.
[SPEAKER_01]: How much effort he has invested in the repetition of that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, moment of death might be enough for sotāpanna, and quite often probably would be, as it was mentioned in the suttas, that, oh yeah, yeah, that is the complete dispassion, release, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they're dying, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they have no more room for any distraction, or carelessness, or complacency.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if that doesn't happen, yeah, there won't be... what the Buddha tell us then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they won't be reborn short in a human, and it will be at most seven lifetimes, not more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I understand these lifetimes, more like in traditional way, basically die, and then you... Well, yeah, but not necessarily as a human.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might be higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically, seven more returns.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seven more reappearances, re-emergence, at most.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it can be two and a half.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking, actually, maybe seven... number seven is more metaphorical, because sometimes number just means, like, I don't know, there are five hundred islands, which just mean exactly five hundred.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, like, just a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seven means few.
[SPEAKER_00]: Few.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, actually, yes, probably.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as you read, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: And even when it comes to ānāgāmīs, like, I'm normally telling he's going to be impurable, but then you read that, I think, in ānāgāmī saṃyutta, they're like all these different types of heavens, like, I don't know, with thirty or something, based on the different fact how strong the ānāgāmīs were in their understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's basically just like one gradual development,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then the Buddha laid out milestones for, just as an incentive, as a guideline, as a kind of clarification, as a sort of a place of confidence as well, because you can, you know, you understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you have... before the Buddha described what sotāpanna is, the actual sotāpannas would have understood the dharma and be free from three fetters.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't have known, or most certainly they wouldn't have known, that they cannot be the One Lord and a human.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be reborn more than seven times.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't have known that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by saying, by defining, it's like, oh, yeah, so then they do feel the release and kind of a sense of freedom and accomplishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's quite important as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, in a similar manner, by defining what sotāpati is, in terms of which factors you're free from, and what sotāpati can do, what sotāpati cannot do, whether his intention is
[SPEAKER_01]: Similar things you read in suttas, then, actually, it clarifies what you need to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, actually, it kind of defines the work, defines the object for your contemplation, because if you do understand, you would be the one.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no, like, in between, like, no, I understand, but I'm not sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you can't have that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you either understand, in which case you're a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, am I a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only way of thinking that can actually then keep you coding... coding you on towards understanding the sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's anything in between, that compromise will obstruct.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you are able to hold a contradiction of, yes, I know, and at the same time know that you're the one who doesn't know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a massive contradiction of a very fundamental existential importance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody can tolerate that, means they cannot become a sotāpanna, because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it has to be black and white.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people are like, you know, well, that's... yeah, it's harsh.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what do you want?
[SPEAKER_01]: You want harsh?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you want easy, that can kind of keep you putridjana, or harsh, that can sort of make you sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not harsh.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's harsh only because you're sensitive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, if a person thinks, I'm only a sotāpanna, nobody shorter than
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, then, any notion of their understanding of the dhamma, unless they're sotāpanna, they will not take for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, they will eventually understand what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they take it for... if they take it as that which they have understood, they won't be making a further effort to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they will take it as that which they have understood, if they are able to maintain contradiction of saṅgadhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, at the same time, know that they're not sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we've made quite a... sotāpanna doesn't have doubts anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it comes to some passages in the Sutta, and when we see it, can we say, oh, I'm sorry, I don't understand that one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, probably.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like we probably mentioned the eight motivations and some other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, because there's so many, so many different ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they're all ways along the same universal principle, but they're different approaches, and they're different expositions, and different descriptions, and yeah, I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of those people back in the day, they haven't heard it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if they were to dwell on it, or if they were to talk more about it, I'm sure they would see it within the principles.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... not, you know, not by default.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, suddenly they know everything, and everyone who ever said them, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So basically, the Sutta Pāṇḍa stage would be really a recognition that all these things, this kind of... it's impossible, actually, to own five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they would stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would basically cease to assume.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a separate center of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: The center of experience that is basically independent of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's independent of anything that appears for it, which is the ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot think that anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by not being able to think that anymore, all they would see is five resonating, five aggregates ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, all these aggregates would more feel like it belongs more there, rather than actually something that belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, but see, that, yeah, describing like that would imply a comparison between how it feels with Atavāda and how it feels without Atavāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, they will, the sattvana will feel released shortly after abolishing Atavāda, but then that is the normal state, so he has no old reference anymore to compare to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means that's it now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was there in the very beginning, it didn't belong to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I mean is, he doesn't have the old reference of ātravāda to compare to the new reference of, oh, no, things don't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has a memory of it, but any kind of emotional release, there will be initially, upon understanding, until things settle.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, afterwards, he cannot go back and kind of have the experience of ātravāda and then compare it to the experience of the non-ātravāda, which is what you compared, basically, when you said, like, oh, in terms of how much release, there is no...
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that would require him to still be able to access Atharvāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he can still access Atharvāda, you know, free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't abolished it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't need much of remembering his right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: He remains mindless and kept... Well, yeah, because the right view is what his center of experience is now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all he has to do, really, is not actively distract himself from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if he stops distracting, automatically the mind will go back to what it's based on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for Sotāpanna, it's based upon the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: For Putujana, it's based upon Atharv
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, it's like he cannot anymore control... he realizes, in the first place, he was not actually controlling the feeling, the perception, and so on, the whole nature... Yeah, there was no separate entity of self apart from those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if he still remains... if he's still affected by those things to some degree, which a Sotāpanna would be, he would be just to a degree that he still might
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, he couldn't possibly take things in such a permanent manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you were to make the effort to do so, it would be inconceivable for him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why it would be inconceivable for him is because things were truly impossible to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why arahantship is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: By finding that out, you have then, eh... basically, undone the mistake of not knowing that it was impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, once you do that mistake, you can't go back to it, even if you think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... it doesn't... that it can't... it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he didn't... he didn't know before.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had a vijja.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eh... That's why he was mistaking that notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is why most of the time, it's kind of belonging, basically, kind of solicitation for taṃkhā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Praying maybe is too gross for me, so I feel like... No, I think it's the other way around, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think longing is more... Not longing, like leaning towards, like... for it, you know, like leaning towards the perception for me, just kind of, just very subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, people kind of realize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then it's still time that this old dhamma diminishes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he still has habits, but he still also has a sense of I am, in terms of conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Yeah, it's not as much as for Putujana, who is, like, fully self-centered in a completely assumed, gratuitous center of ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: But still...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only for an ārahant, you can truly say that all he has left are the habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, Dīpānanda still has a good three quarters of responsibility for his habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: Especially if we're talking about habits of lust, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which are really not habits then.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's impossible if he doesn't take responsibility for his actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't ignore it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or he can ignore it only up to a certain extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because all he has to do is stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: To take a break from all the distraction and unwholesome habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: And at that time, he will be looking at his right view, from his right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: He just... that is his place of rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: All he has to do is not distract himself, not sort of get careless, in the sense of take... And then, it would, at most, in seven lifetimes, basically, I mean, anyway, but if he wants it faster, all he needs to do is practice restraint, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, all that has to be done is to put the stick back to the water.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are things which are already read in Sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, if I re-read again, Here, with destruction of things, the bhikkhu has realized for himself direct knowledge, in this very life, the taintless liberation of mind, liberation by wisdom, and having entered upon it, he dwells in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is listed in Sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it mean this thing sattvāsa doesn't have, or it's just
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it talks about arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: It didn't enter the eight municipations yet.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it says, here with the destruction of the three factors, diminishing of greed, hatred and delusion, bhikkhus want to return there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who after coming back to this world, who after coming back to this world one more time, will make an end to suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the next paragraph, that you say, here with the destruction of the taint, the bhikkhu has realized for himself direct knowledge in this very life that taint is liberation of mind, liberation by wisdom, having entered upon it, he dwells in it, yet he does not dwell having contacted with the body the eight emancipations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, I see, the last bit is different.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, he dwells in it, he does not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I thought, just I've read in the first sentence, that's arahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, but even that, I think, well, I guess... No, this can be also said, basically, for a
[SPEAKER_01]: Because Sotāpanna knows what nibbāna is, and he can enter upon it with wisdom, liberation by wisdom, and he can be dwelling in it, but for as long as his body, the phenomenon of the body, I don't want to say like body enters some mystical experience, but for as long as that body does not get established in it, he won't be in nibbāna as an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is the same nibbāna, it is the same understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, yeah, even Sotāpanna has the notion of the right knowledge and right liberation, but it's a very weak notion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said, on the other hand, he's fully developed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, the difference between Sotāpanna and Sakadāgāmī is basically that, like you said, Sakadāgāmī is just more developed Sotāpanna, and
[SPEAKER_00]: One indifference which we find, so to speak, has also the right knowledge and the right liberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it says, he was contemplating rising and seizing the five aggregates, subject to assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's also Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not much difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, with a distraction of the five lower fetters, the bhikkhu is one of spontaneous birth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Due to attaining vāni-nibbāna, there, without returning,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think that just... that just stands for the... the very, very refined
[SPEAKER_01]: type of rebirth, so to speak, which will automatically lead him to arahantship there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he was basically almost an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to that degree of residue, to that degree of almost, eh... he's going to have a rebirth in one of the purer boats, as they call it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, I told you that Sāṃyātmikā is just... just, I don't know, dozens of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like one place for all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just depending how much residue he had left.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can't measure that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the Buddha couldn't measure that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so subtle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he said, he will attain the final liberation here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if there isn't any residue left, he'll go to the pure abode and then be finished there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... And that's why often anāgāmīs would have overestimated themselves and thinking they were arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they couldn't tell.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha would only be able to tell by seeing the mind, but
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, anāgāmī, you know, that's already a person free from sensuality, aversion, virtually free from all the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, he still could not tell, because it's just so, so subtle, leftover.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's that subtle, it doesn't matter, because they're going to have a spontaneous rebirth in such a refined realm, reserved only for such beings, and he'll be going up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Might be very soon upon landing again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Might be a bit longer, might be a bit much more longer, you know, now they won't just... yeah, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there's some sort of somewhere that actually says, you know, it could be quite a durevic jump from sotāpanna to arahantship, but what prevents to go to all the way to arahantship and he remains to be anāgāmī is he's the life and dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just kind of stuck there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think he's kind of holding on the last thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I remember that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not relinquishing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe to be a little bit excited.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like just not looking back thoroughly at the right view that brought him to that place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just completely... because even that, even that right view, you just completely develop this passion towards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Discuss, dispassion, relinquishment, everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you're fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it's really just extinguished.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they might not necessarily do that sufficiently.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might not necessarily experience complete nibbida towards the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And... And the most interesting things, uh... is he draws having contacted...
[SPEAKER_00]: Contacted with a body.
[SPEAKER_00]: The eight emancipations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Shall I go to the eight emancipations?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, what is the Pali word?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the translation of emancipation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Atavimokkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, like liberation, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Shall I just read first?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: One possessing rūpa, sees rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: One not perceiving the rūpa internally, sees rūpa externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: One is released upon the idea of the beautiful, or translation can be, one is focused only on the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fourth one is, through the complete surmounting of perception of rūpa, the passing away of perception of impingement and content, and non-attention to perception of diversity, perceiving in brackets, space is infinite, one enters and dwells in the base of infinity of space.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fifth one is the same things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is infinite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sixth, there's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seventh, neither perception nor non-perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eighth, sensation and perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just first four were really interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the... the point is, they're not like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, they are eight different, but not eight different in a sense of one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's basically one,
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, you can go to the second one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, you can go to the third one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, you can go to the fourth one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have one, technically, you contemplate all of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But how far up that one you will go, that's the... that's basically how refined, in terms of development, your mind gets.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, does it mean every... every ārya-pūgala has got to do all these things, or...?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, not ārya-pūgala.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ānagāmī and... and arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not all.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So
[SPEAKER_01]: They contact that principle of such a liberation, which means they get one.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: One single part?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the first one, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, start with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, they can, you know, is there beyond?
[SPEAKER_01]: As sometimes you read in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they go further, and further, and further, until they go, what?
[SPEAKER_01]: The ultimate, there is no beyond.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it was a similar description when he came to Jhānas, in that Sariputra, in Majjhima Nikāya, one by one.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he comes to cessation of sexual feeling, he says, there is no beyond this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sotāpanna and sakadāgāmī have not contacted with the body, the principle of self-liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: They understood these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_00]: They understand this phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think, because even those eight phenomena are probably along the same lines that, say, Sotāpanna would have developed his mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he would have started getting the principle of the mind development.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, that he hasn't contacted it with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means he hasn't really experienced those liberations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if he experienced... Well, connecting with the body means basically making such experience actual, present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just resolved upon wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can clear it up with the wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, actually, you haven't been establishing your mind in it, in the sense that, now, that experience is what is present for you, actually, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, going with body wouldn't be levitating to some mystical state?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Contacting with the body just means making it actual, as opposed to, like, a peripheral understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it can be very... That's how, like, people can resolve upon wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: upon the element of nibbāna, and become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't mean that it's all just put to... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have the element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to understand what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if the mind gets resolved upon it, it will drag the body into the actual experience of it, if the mind doesn't give up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where the paññavimutti, like liberated through wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, he he kind of shoots his mind out there towards the right principle that he's understood through the clarity of his wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's actually quite far removed in terms of actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing is an actual, eh, recent phenomenon, that nibbāna, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: touching it with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if your mind stays in it, the body will eventually catch up with it, and then he would say, yeah, he was liberated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you have those whose mind is developed, they're not necessarily understanding all the, all the subtleties of nibbāna, but they clearly have the mind developed to the extent of, yeah, they're actually experiencing that with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of the undetermined element.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they can, they, they're experiencing, they can hold on to it, they can have it.
[SPEAKER_01]: present, as opposed to, you know, it's not like a momentary zone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's like when people are sort of liberated both ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in this case, basically, it's that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these eight, just think of it as one, and think of that one as standing as a description of touching you with the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, within that, you can keep refining that to the point of cessation, perception, and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can become fully enlightened just by touching the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just by getting the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how important it is now to understand this sutta?
[SPEAKER_01]: What sutta?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that sutta just gives you the ultimate perfect scenario of going through all the eight.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in the same sense, whenever jhānas go, they go through all four.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, whenever the material establishments of mind are described, again, they're all described.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, there are other suttas where the Buddha said it's the strength of the first jhāna is enough for arhantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anāgāmī needs to understand the first jhāna and he can become fully enlightened, arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he might not have necessarily touched with the body the seventh and the eighth of those, eh, liberations, but he certainly touched them all in a sense that the principle, which is kind of the first one, the second one, and so on, has been understood and has been touched with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would it be okay if we got one by one, at least the first four?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one possessing rūpas is rūpa?
[SPEAKER_01]: This, I assume, is just... Well, see, now, this can be a long discussion, because it's a subtle thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, if I were to sort of describe it in words to you, then we have to sort of address the meaning of those words as well, and then I might have to do the meaning of those words as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, most concisely, basically, the experience consists of two points of view simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: One coming from the direction of the conscious body present in the world, and another one coming from the point of view of, basically, uh... nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are two points of view at once, which is why reflection is possible, which is why
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahantship is possible, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if there is only one point of view, to your experience, right there and then, eh... there would be a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There would be a center.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always two.
[SPEAKER_01]: There cannot be one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there's always two, there cannot be one self.
[SPEAKER_01]: There cannot be one conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, two points of view are one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine you become very skilled.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always two points of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what five aggregates are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's two points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two things simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two directions, two points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't come together, they don't meet, they don't cross.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just two points of view with their respective directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, because you have two points of view, you can sometimes see the same thing twice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean that you see it independent of those points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means you recognize that thing is doubly present.
[SPEAKER_01]: It appears in both directions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no outside of those directions, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, your attention can only be resting on one point of view or the other point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the assumption of the external in regard to the two points of view that causes the whole confusion and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine you have removed all the confusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now you just have two points of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and the person that confuses the two points of view is the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't even see the two points of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just me, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, imagine you remove the confusion in regard to the two points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the possibilities are endless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not endless.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will land in cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with one point of view, you cannot perceive the other point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: With one point of view, you can perceive the other point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: With the other point of view, you can perceive the other point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or with the other point of view, you cannot perceive the other point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you mean, while not perceiving rūpa internally, it sees rūpa externally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I would basically cover the four.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can sort of move along, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: All to the point of, when you basically stop giving attention to either points of view, and then that's... that's the cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that would pertain to the... to the other... other four, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in between the two points of view, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not externally, just basically not based on the two points of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby, it will culminate in cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cessation of the both points of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: The word beautiful in the third line is a bit interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: The idea of beautiful, or focus on the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there's another...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it's in the sense of another sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, he sees beautiful in ugly, or he sees ugly in the beautiful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I'm coming to the sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's again, it's along the same things, because the subhanimitta, it's obviously always on the basis of what is kind of
[SPEAKER_01]: A nimitta.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that nimitta is always basically a subha, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I first read it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just maybe make it more clear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recording.
[SPEAKER_00]: One percipient of forms internally, sees forms externally, limited, beautiful and ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: One percipient of forms internally, sees forms externally, measureless, beautiful or ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: One non-percipient of forms internally, sees forms externally, limited, beautiful or ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: One not recipient of forms internally, sees forms externally, measureless, beautiful or ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: One not recipient of forms internally, sees forms externally, blue ones, blue in color, with a blue tint.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there goes 6 is yellow, 7 is red, and 8 is white.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first one is a slight vice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recipient of forms internally,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can see beautiful in ugly, or you can see ugly in beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically, discerning that, that that depends upon the two point of view present at once, you will see that, well, beautiful in terms of intoxication loses its power, because you just see
[SPEAKER_01]: Beautiful that's simultaneously seen as ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could just resolve upon seeing the beautiful in everything that is really around you, which is ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you could resolve to see ugly in everything that's beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is dispassion in regard to the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only when people have one point of view and what they have presented
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, when they assume one point of view, and what they have presented in front of them is the beautiful, there's that kind of mesmerizing and lust and so on with the beautiful, mind is locked upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you see it simultaneously, just simultaneously present, again, as another point of view, automatically cannot be as beautiful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the second one is about...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first one was like it's limited, but then becomes measureless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Infinite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, finer arises on the basis of infinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only because it's possible for things to be infinite, they can be finer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, a finer thing, a defined thing, right in front of you, that has arisen to your point of view, you discern the other point of view, becoming through that thing, and then you see, yeah, it's on the basis of infinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: The
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of a point of view, one of the point of view, or the nature of the point of view, the nature of the direction, is that infinity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start seeing that while the finite thing is present in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with limitless you see limited, or with measureless you see limited, or with limited you see measureless.
[SPEAKER_01]: It really depends just what point of view you attend to, and what aspect of the point of view you attend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, the purpose of that is the full discussion in regards to the five elements, the structure of the experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to really say that one reflects at least one to eight?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: That one is anything better than the second one?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, like the casinos, the black casinos, you can develop a full alignment chip upon one, upon the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, maybe, if somebody else has found the second one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, maybe, if somebody has found the third one.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not, you know, up to ten, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean you have to go one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten, nine, eight, eleven, twelve, thirteen, fourteen, fifteen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, eight casinos.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, there's only four casinos, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I thought, in general, the other casinos, there's one, I think, there are ten casinos.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: The four elements, the
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't matter, because the first kāsina is already... the principle of kāsina is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just refining the same principle that you get in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's interesting, when they're using these four colors.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is exactly the four colors when Buddha was talking about what's perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perception is blue, yellow, red and white.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a nice
[SPEAKER_00]: Sutra... just a verse, I should say.
[SPEAKER_00]: "...having touched with the body the deathless element free from clinging, having realized the relinquishing of clinging, his stains are gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fully enlightened one proclaims the sorrowless state that is void of state."
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, with arahant, says, "...here is the destruction of the
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, a bhikkhu has realized for himself with direct knowledge, in this very life, the painless liberation of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Liberation by wisdom, and having entered upon it, he dwells in it, and he also, ah, dwells, and having contacted with the body, the eight emancipations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, he, he dwells in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's his actual experience, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when those, I think, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think in the notes, there's one...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it was disagreements on translation, I can't remember what it was, but, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: He mentions that, like, oh, there are many suttas they would kind of show.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would kind of show how, like, an ārya would sort of fall away from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they had problems, sort of, not falling...
[SPEAKER_01]: They had problems not falling away from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when they committed suicide, or things like that, because they had, kind of, ah...
[SPEAKER_01]: They all got sick and then they couldn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it's one thing to understand nibbāna, to kind of develop it, but to sort of fully develop it to the point of that becoming your basis of the... You know how you replace ātavāda with the right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then replace that right view with like a fully sort of just relinquished, undetermined element, the element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that takes time to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's a noble, faithful path, kind of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eightfold, sort of, covering different aspects of it as needed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because some people would be because of this, some people would be falling away because of that, and that's why some people fall away less, or fall away less far.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have different areas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have, within the defined areas, you have different types.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a really weak Sotāpanna, there's a barely Sotāpanna, there's a strong Sotāpanna, there's this, there's... because they get reborn in different places, because of a different strength.
[SPEAKER_00]: These four kinds of beings, the noble ones, of course, can be also taken scarefully, for people maybe grasping wrongly, and for boosting their ego.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people have to go to another extreme, or it's just metaphorical, and just be here and now, and don't think about these four stages.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people would say it's just like a carrot and a donkey, keeps encouraging.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, there's nothing wrong with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But probably, this is actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think it's better to accept them as criterias, because if you don't, then you won't be making effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people say, ah, don't try to become anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they would say that only because they haven't become anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then they start dismissing the goal of becoming something valuable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it's... No, become a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is what you're supposed to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sotāpanna becomes sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's good, actually, to wish to become sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Talk about it, in fact, in this temple.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_01]: When somebody hears, oh, such and such is an arahant, such and such is sotāpanna, oh, well, I can do it then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because of that craving, he actually makes the effort and does it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if the one who hears about somebody becomes sotāpanna, or somebody becomes an arahant, says, oh, well, there
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why the Buddha was encouraging such aim, so that you can crave for it, and because of craving, you can make the effort, because of which, you would abandon that craving, and then actually become one, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, only people who have got anywhere, and they didn't get anywhere in the practice, would be dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Who would say... they would say things like, oh, there's not to be... don't try to become anything, there's just another becoming, or they would say things like, the more you practice, the less you know, and I've been 30 years in robes, and, you know, I feel like I know even less, as if that's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should be embarrassed to say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The longer you are in robes, without becoming sotāpanna, means more... more of the time you're wasting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you're actually... should be more embarrassed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine there is something you need to learn, something you need to get fixed, and you
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you meet somebody who can't fix it for 10 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would say, he's pretty, pretty co-operative, isn't he?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you wouldn't take advice from him, wouldn't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you take advice from somebody who fixed it in two days?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or from somebody who couldn't fix it in 10 years?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you take advice on how to fix it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who would you choose from?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, it's basically just people indulging their own weakness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the... they haven't got anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because they lack faculties, not because they lack support, not because they lack health.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because they lack determination, they lack faith, they lack clarity, they lack the five enlightenment factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uh, and then they indulge that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then they make that to be the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, not getting anywhere is the goal of the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, because that certainly is not the goal of the Buddhist practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were, he would have said so.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would have not said entirely the opposite thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, my thing was that... My thing was understood as the monks, monks themselves were quite
[SPEAKER_00]: Not quite clear, maybe, but there was always some knowledge who attained what.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe things were spoken up.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now this goal is never actually spoken.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because nobody attained anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they just hope that other people will assume that he has attained.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know what they hope for, but the only reason they don't speak about attainments is because they don't know what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they know about it, they will be speaking about it, because that's just along the lines of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it shouldn't be actually a taboo question?
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you should be careful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should be careful in terms of, you know, some people in the past have used it and used it to gain the offerings and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, of course it shouldn't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's a personal thing, so you don't want to take it too casually if you're asking somebody about it, because it can just come disrespectful and then they won't tell you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, you're just asking casually and that's not a casual thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no, of course, it's not, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you were a Buddha, the Buddha wouldn't have spoken about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, I was asked for the environmental practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sotāpanna, basically, can practice in the... for attaining sotāpanna, the environment, can be in the family, can be in the workspace?
[SPEAKER_00]: Not anymore, I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, theoretically, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in the Buddha's time, because at those days, there was the world,
[SPEAKER_01]: hasn't been proliferated as much as it is today.
[SPEAKER_01]: The availabilities of distraction, the freedom from fear or anxiety, sickness, aging, death around you, we're all kind of sheltered from it, it's all quickly covered, it's all quickly fixed, it's all quickly sort of painted over, plus all the distractions, sensuality, manifold kind of ways of getting it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, were you required a lot of effort to step back from the pull of the world and society?
[SPEAKER_01]: Too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Too much effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had a lot of effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would require too much effort for a today's person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Back in the day, when the world did not have as much pull in terms of its proliferation, in terms of its diversification, then, yeah, they could have.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what would be your advice or to make hope
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they have to leave the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have to leave the lay life.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be a layman and expect it to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was hard back...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the Buddha's day, they would say, oh, lay life is crowded and dusty and we have so much to do and so many responsibilities we can't practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine today.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a
[SPEAKER_01]: Just a mass of clutter is absolutely not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, a layperson can't...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean he can't become a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Theoretically, sure, he doesn't need to put the rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's nothing special with the ropes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an external statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what a layperson needs to do is drastically change their living environment, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: not live as a common layperson.
[SPEAKER_01]: And today, in pretty much, practically speaking, the way to change that environment is to find a forest monastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can do it, but as a layman, going, yeah, sure, you can, and it is possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, but, yeah, I think it's important to to recognize that back in the Buddha's day, it was hard as a layperson.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two and a half thousand years later, it's virtually impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the effort doesn't mean that you have to sit like many hours meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, we try to read the sutta and try to understand and lay the conclusion...
[SPEAKER_01]: The effort means they have to sit for many hours trying to understand the meaning of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many hours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many days.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many times.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if they actually spend the time sitting doing a meditation technique, well, they'll be better off as a generous layman.
[SPEAKER_01]: They'll be less misguided, probably.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as a layman who doesn't try to practice dhamma, but is just being generous in virtues.
[SPEAKER_01]: But instead of... if they sit cross-legged, watching their nostril, observing their belly, they should sit for many hours, or walk for many hours, and keep drilling with the standing of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is... what are the... what are the factors?
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand the nature of the factors?
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be free from them.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are the four noble truths?
[SPEAKER_01]: See the four noble truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: See the principle of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will be realizing them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that won't happen by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That won't happen if you sit cross-legged and watch your breath, or do any other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the main things you have to learn is really how to contemplate, because people can go to another extreme.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, meditation got into entirely things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say trying to understand, I don't mean like doing scholarly work and fixing out the declinations of Pali, Pali terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean actually trying to understand the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see how
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it sounds very vague to people.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason for that is because the thinking is so far removed from any form of correct thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just the concept of thinking is, it seems so vague.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, how do I think about it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Give me an object.
[SPEAKER_01]: An object is... pick... read the sutra.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the object.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's why people struggle.
[SPEAKER_01]: They think like, what is... what has to be the object of my thought, then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they can't comprehend thinking without this clearly defined object.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well,
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about the nature of your sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see how ambiguous that is for most people.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means the more ambiguous it is, the more far removed from it you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you won't fix that by sort of finding a completely different object to think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you'll fix it by thinking about it and begin to try to clarify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Read the suttas, get the info you can, drill it, think about it, and then it will become clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start discerning your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're making the effort to discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't make the effort to discern it, if you make the effort to do some, I don't know, mechanical technique, or to be thinking about a particular mantra, or something else, but you never discern the ambiguity of your senses, or of your nature of the thoughts, or anything, or feelings, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's ambiguous only because it's not clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not clear because there was never any effort made towards clarification of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and then, actually, you know, for someone who is aiming for high development lucid abhāna,
[SPEAKER_00]: You would say that, actually, complete seclusion is necessary, giving more away from distractions?
[SPEAKER_01]: For an authentic person, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: For a person who is not running away from things, but for a person who is actively making the effort in overcoming them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're talking about from sotāpanna, I'm telling... Ah, sorry, no, I'm talking about laymen, sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody is already a sotāpanna, if they want to become... yeah, yeah, he has to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, back in the day, it would have been maybe possible living in the outskirts, depending on the village, independence on the village, and so on, and kind of having interaction with others.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think even back then, to put a cap sort of exhorting monks, there are empty huts, there are empty roots of trees, empty forests, empty jungle, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So today, imagine how much more you have to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Back then, you can go for a retreat like that, do the work, and then, you know, come back to a more comfortable setting.
[SPEAKER_00]: But today, I think,
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs to be much, much more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there hope for arrogant-ship in this present moment?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's hope as long as there is hope for becoming a sadhpāna.